<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[git | Andreas Renberg (IQAndreas)]]></title>
  <link href="http://IQAndreas.github.com/posts/categories/git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://IQAndreas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-03T22:17:01+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://IQAndreas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andreas Renberg (IQAndreas)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Best practices for git ignore]]></title>
    <link href="http://IQAndreas.github.com/git/best-practices-for-git-ignore/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-02T11:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://IQAndreas.github.com/git/best-practices-for-git-ignore</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/">man pages for GIT</a> aren't usually the clearest or most helpful, and is seldom the first place I turn to for help. Still, I ran across some valuable "best practices" information which I myself have not been following due to ignorance.<!-- more --></p>

<p>I thought the only place to mark which files to hide was inside of a <code>.gitignore</code> file, ideally placed at the root of the repository. As a result, I would list all files and folders I may want to ignore inside of it. [<a href="https://github.com/FlixelCommunity/flixel/blob/dev/.gitignore">1</a>]</p>

<p>Instead, GIT has provided us with four places to provide <a href="http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/gitignore.html#_pattern_format"><em>file name patterns</em></a>, each with its own intended purpose <em>(some descriptions have been taken verbatim from the docs)</em>:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Sent as command line arguments</strong> <em>(Only supported by some commands)</em> - Mostly only useful for scripts or "temporary exceptions".</p></li>
<li><p><strong>A .gitignore file in the project directory</strong> - Patterns which should be version-controlled and distributed to other repositories via clone (i.e., files that <em>all</em> developers will want to ignore)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>In the file .git/info/exclude</strong> - Patterns which are specific to a particular repository but which do not need to be shared with other related repositories (e.g., auxiliary files that live inside the repository but are specific to one user's workflow)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>In the configuration variable core.excludesfile</strong> - Patterns which a user wants GIT to ignore in <em>all</em> situations (e.g., backup or temporary files generated by the user’s editor of choice). Note that you can set the <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2114111/where-does-git-config-global-get-written-to">global config value</a>, so every single project you work on will always ignore those pesky files such as <code>Thumbs.db</code>.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>There are also further technical details in which ignores take precedence etc. in case anyone wants some heavier reading:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/gitignore.html"><img class="favicon" src="http://www.kernel.org/favicon.ico"> <em>gitignore(5) Manual Page</em></a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
